U.S. Emergency Board No. 138 Records 5058
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board No. 138 Records
1961
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. Emergency Board
5058
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Maps, proceedings, transcripts.
Transcript of proceedings and exhibits of the Emergency Board No. 138, 1961. Southern Pacific Company (Pacific Lines) vs. Order of Railroad Telegraphers, 1950-1961.
3336723
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 29, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 04, 2019
Biographical / Historical
U.S. Emergency Board No. 138 was created in 1961 by President Kennedy in response to a strike called by the Order of Railroad Telegraphers against the Southern Pacific Railroad Co.
A dispute arose when the Telegraphers, in response to severe job cutbacks due to abandonments and automation, requested that no position in existence as of April 1st, 1958 be abolished or discontinued except by agreement between the carrier and the Telegraphers. The union invoked mediation because the parties were unable to come to any agreement. Before the mediation efforts were exhausted, the Telegraphers proposed rules which barred unilateral transfer of any functions, work and positions performed or held by telegraphers; required payment of severence pay to displaced workers? and guaranteed a certain minimum to telegraphers when they consented to the merger or consolidation of jobs. Negotiations were continued but when no agreement was reached, the Telegraphers successfully requested the service of the National Mediation Board again.
The Board was appointed in July and met that month and the following August. Reporting in September, the Board concluded that the union's position as stated was "Neither a practical nor realistic solution to the problem of employee displacement" and recommended that the carrier and union agree to protections for adversely affected employees, including dismissal pay, moving expenses and property loss allowances.
Scope and Contents
Transcript of proceedings and exhibits of the Emergency Board No. 138, 1961. Southern Pacific Company (Pacific Lines) vs. Order of Railroad Telegraphers, 1950-1961.
The collection includes transcripts of proceedings (14 vol.); carrier exhibits including maps, agreements, statistics on population, income, comparative railroad revenue, passenger and freight statistics, data on fringe benefits, social security, railroad unemployment, insurance and other data for Class 1 railroads (1950-1959); employees' exhibits including statistics on agencies closed and union positions abolished on the Southern Pacific Railroad, employment and productivity trends, employment stabilization agreements, and rules prohibiting or controlling contracting out of work, among other matters.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5006: U.S. Emergency Board No. 174 Records 5007: U.S. Emergency Board No. 175 Transcripts and Exhibits 5012: Saul Wallen Papers 5027: U.S. Emergency Board No. 178 Transcripts 5030: U.S. Emergency Board No. 179 Exhibits and Related Material 5036: U.S. Emergency Boards under the Railway Labor Act Reports 5037: U.S. Emergency Board No. 81 Records 5038: U.S. Emergency Board No. 94 Records 5039: U.S. Emergency Board No. 98 Records 5040: U.S. Emergency Board No. 106 Records 5042: U.S. Emergency Board No. 111 Records 5043: U.S. Emergency Board No. 114 Records 5044: U.S. Emergency Board No. 116 Reports and Exhibits 5045: U.S. Emergency Board No. 118 Records 5046: U.S. Emergency Board No. 119 Records 5047: U.S. Emergency Board No. 120 Records 5048: U.S. Emergency Board No. 121 Records 5050: U.S. Emergency Board No. 124 Records 5051: U.S. Emergency Board No. 125 Records 5052: U.S. Emergency Board No. 129 Records 5053: U.S. Emergency Board No. 130 Records 5054: U.S. Emergency Board No. 133 Exhibits 5055: U.S. Emergency Board No. 134 Records 5056: U.S. Emergency Board No. 135 Records 5057: U.S. Emergency Board No. 137 Transcript of Proceedings and Exhibits 5059: U.S. Emergency Board No. 142 Records 5060: U.S. Emergency Board No. 145 Records 5061: U.S. Emergency Board No. 146 Records 5062: U.S. Emergency Board No. 154 Records 5064: U.S. Emergency Board No. 169 Transcript of Proceedings and Exhibits 5075: U.S. Emergency Board under the Taft Hartley Act Records 5579: National Mediation Board Emergency Board 180, Train Crew Consists 5934: Arthur Stark Papers on the President's Emergency Board #219 5058 P: U.S. Emergency Board No. 138 Photographs
Mediation and conciliation, Industrial -- United States x Cases.; Unemployment, Technological-- United States.; Arbitration, Industrial--United States-- Sources.; Railroads--Employees--Labor unions--United States--Sources.; Telegraphers.; Job descriptions. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Job security. Arbitration, Industrial. United States.; Job security. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. Railroads. United States.; Railroads. United States. Technological innovations.; Strikes and lockouts. Railroads. United States.; Wages. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Wages. Railroads. United States.; Work rules. Mediation and conciliation, Industrial. United States.; Order of Railroad Telegraphers (U.S.); Southern Pacific Company; United States. Emergency Board No. 138.
3336723
- Transcripts, Carrier's Agreements, Employee's Agreements, Joint Agreements (Box 1)
  - Transcripts. 14 Volumes. 2018 Pages. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Map - Southern Pacific Lines in red (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Maintenance of Way Agreement and notice in connection therewith (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Decision of the Public Utility Commission of Oregon, Order Number 37014 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Decision covers the application of Southern Pacific Company for authority to withdraw its agent at Brownsville, Oregon.
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Map of Southern Pacific Company (Pacific Lines), Coast Division, indicating location of Vandenberg Air Force Base. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Population, Income, Railroad Revenue, Return on Investment for Industry, Passenger and Freight Statistics, Material Prices, and related information (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Carrier's Exhibit 5a. Classifications according to International Chamber of Congress Group Number. 5b. Southern Pacific number of employees in International Chamber of Congress Group IV, Transportation.
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Reporting Divisions 111-128 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Excerpts from various reports (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Retirement, Sickness Benefits, Social Security, Railroad Unemployment, Insurance Statistics. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Pictures - Centralized Traffic Control (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Pictures - Centralized Traffic Control - Interlocks (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. "Agency Closings" (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Clerks' Agreement. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Board awards. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Book - Statement of Claims, Employee's Statements at Hearings. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Case Number A-1146 - CTC (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Rule requested by the Switchmen's Union of North America, together with an employee protection agreement requested by the clerks (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. List of Western Railroads which did not have any dialyzing agreements as of June 8, 1954. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    June 8, 1954.
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Composite income account, balance sheet, and other statistics of Class I railroads including switching and terminal companies, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Southern Pacific operating ratio compared with operating ratios of Class I railroads, 1951-1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Carrier's Exhibit. Ratio of Southern Pacific as compared to Class I railroads - net railway operating income. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "History of the Disputes." (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Employees' Exhibits. Agencies Closed and Order of Railroad Telegraphers Positions abolished on the Southern Pacific Company. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Employment and Output Trends, Southern Pacific Company and Class I Line - Haul Railways." (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "The Public Interest in Transportation Service." (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Excerpts from Carrier Presentation to Emergency Board Number 106." (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Work within the scope of the Order of Railroad Telegraphers-Southern Pacific Company Agreement transferred to other Personnel." (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Employment Stabilization Agreements and understandings in the railroad industry." (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Examples of Dualization Agreements made by the Order of Railroad Telegraphers with various Carriers." (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Employment Stabilization Agreements in Other American Industries." (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Rules prohibiting or controlling contracting out of work." (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Employee Protection in the Railroad Industry." (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Employees' Exhibit 11a. Agreement for Employee Protection as a result of the merger of Norfolk and Western Railway Company and the Virginian Railway Company.
  - Employees' Exhibits. "Financial position of the Southern Pacific Company." (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Employees' Exhibits. Award of Special Board of Adjustment Number 327 - Case Number 1 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Employees' Exhibits. Award of Special Board of Adjustment Number 327 - Case Number 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Employees' Exhibits. Award of Special Board of Adjustment Number 327 - Case Number 3. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Employees' Exhibits. Interstate Commerce Commission Form M-300. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Joint Exhibit - Agreement between Southern Pacific Company and employees represented by Order of Railroad Telegraphers (Box 1, Folder 38)